<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title><generator uri="https://perun.io/" version="0.4.3-SNAPSHOT">Perun</generator><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/" type="text/html"></link><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/atom.xml" rel="first"></link><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/atom.xml" rel="last"></link><updated>2021-07-27T09:16:18Z</updated><id>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/</id><entry><id>urn:uuid:299e8bd0-376e-4c48-bbe6-b6a88d687431</id><title>Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence</title><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-3.html" type="text/html" title="Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-26T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2021-07-26T00:00:00Z</updated><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-3.html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;meta charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;meta content="IE=edge,chrome=1" http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible"&gt;&lt;meta content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0, user-scalable=no" name="viewport"&gt;&lt;link href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Roboto:400,700" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/favicon.png" rel="icon" type="image/png"&gt;&lt;title&gt;Digital Evidence Toolkit&lt;/title&gt;&lt;link href="site.main.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body class="w-80 mw100-ns mw6-l center pv5"&gt;&lt;header&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;&lt;h1 class="f3-s f3-m f3-l tc lh-title mt0 mb4"&gt;The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/header&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(In case you missed it last week, the previous issue of this newsletter, “Wait, digital evidence?” in which we touch on chain of custody and admissibility, &lt;a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-2.html"&gt;can be found here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;_&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's maybe time to clarify a few things about what the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit is and does&lt;/strong&gt;*, from the two original thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content living online is at risk&lt;/strong&gt;. Deletion, link rot, censorship, accidental destruction – you name it. The social internet may be great at surfacing and disseminating information but it's pretty terrible at preserving it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If the goal is prosecution, the standards of research, due diligence and safekeeping are a different ballpark to those of journalistic publication&lt;/strong&gt;. As a journalist, I've seen first-hand how some of this evidence is weighed and cleared by Legal. As co-founder of Airwars, I've seen first-hand the steps we took to ensure our material wouldn't disappear. If my law studies serve me well: both the above fall short of what the courts demand when it comes to evidentiary standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to provide a &lt;strong&gt;proof-of-concept software&lt;/strong&gt; for researchers and small teams sifting through online material. With only one click of the mouse, the material will be &lt;strong&gt;archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody and stored durably&lt;/strong&gt;. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to go back to &lt;strong&gt;search through and annotate&lt;/strong&gt; the material, and to &lt;strong&gt;export working copies&lt;/strong&gt; of said material for publication and dissemination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central claim: a database built thusly can be handed to a prosecutor ten years down the line, and they will be able to say with mathematical certainty: &lt;strong&gt;“the material in this archive is identical and contemporary to the one saved at the time, ten years ago.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want this to be the plastic sealed bag in which evidence is deposited, and which is then kept under watch in an evidence room, where each access is tracked and reported in a log.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s not saying we solved the verification and authenticity questions – quite the contrary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Toolkit only addresses provenance and chain the custody from the moment of record. The content stored very well may be unauthentic, doctored, or fake – but with the Toolkit, it will be adequately preserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And without this preservation, the court won’t have the chance to examine it and to sort the fake from the truthful.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#follow-along" id="follow-along"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Follow along&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technical work is taking place &lt;a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit"&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and is best followed through &lt;a href="https://github.com/orgs/digitalevidencetoolkit/projects/2"&gt;the Kanban board&lt;/a&gt; tracking my progress in delivering a minimum viable product in the next couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've got technical chops and have some spare time in the coming month, please get in touch. I'm looking for reviewers, testers, TypeScript connoisseurs, and browser APIs experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#updates" id="updates"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Updates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've reached out to the Centre for Information Resilience's &lt;a href="https://www.info-res.org/myanmarwitness"&gt;Myanmar Witness project&lt;/a&gt;. It's funded through the UK's Foreign, Commonwealth &amp;amp; Development Office and claim: “All data is independently verified, hashed, and kept safely and securely.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a new Berlin venture called &lt;a href="https://www.berlinartlink.com/2021/06/25/forensic-architecture-investigative-commons-at-hkw"&gt;Investigative Commons&lt;/a&gt;. The group, composed of &lt;a href="https://mnemonic.org/en/about/"&gt;Mnemonic&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.bellingcat.com/about/"&gt;Bellingcat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://forensic-architecture.org/about/agency"&gt;Forensic Architecture&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ecchr.eu/en/about-us/"&gt;ECCHR&lt;/a&gt;, is supported by the &lt;a href="https://www.glanlaw.org/"&gt;Global Legal Action Network&lt;/a&gt;. We're speaking soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;← Back to homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="280" scrolling="no" src="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.substack.com/embed" width="100%"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;footer class="mw6-l mw100-ns center bt"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the generous funding and support of&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="flex"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-bmbf.svg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-okfn.svg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Basile Simon</name></author></entry><entry><id>urn:uuid:fad7914d-f6d0-46ed-ad1b-e31aef50548f</id><title>Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?</title><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-2.html" type="text/html" title="Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-18T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2021-07-18T00:00:00Z</updated><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-2.html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;meta charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;meta content="IE=edge,chrome=1" http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible"&gt;&lt;meta content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0, user-scalable=no" name="viewport"&gt;&lt;link href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Roboto:400,700" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/favicon.png" rel="icon" type="image/png"&gt;&lt;title&gt;Digital Evidence Toolkit&lt;/title&gt;&lt;link href="site.main.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body class="w-80 mw100-ns mw6-l center pv5"&gt;&lt;header&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;&lt;h1 class="f3-s f3-m f3-l tc lh-title mt0 mb4"&gt;The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/header&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href="#newsletter-2-wait-digital-evidence" id="newsletter-2-wait-digital-evidence"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be difficult to explain our ambitions for the Digital Evidence Toolkit without first defining ‘digital evidence,’ a term used to describe any information stored in a digital format that is related to any future or ongoing litigation. This evidence may be stored on physical devices (such as smartphones, computers, or hard drives), or transmitted on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advocacy groups have noted that the storage and preservation of digital evidence, whether it be online or on a device, both come with their own unique set of problems – see for example &lt;a href="https://ibanet-org.zoom.us/rec/play/3xubOfazOciZXoUvGEtxNTOiwaQ1lO4wsGrObKjms0kJOL3DmbCR0JERAlHObEMaK6GH85F7cwJf8hcH.KFL67C_8WMqCUSGa?startTime=1605715248000&amp;amp;&amp;amp;_x_zm_rtaid=uRGfAxH-TOWn_Byx9AncRA.1606221810020.4054607a6db9ce7bad94be8bf9561faf&amp;amp;&amp;amp;_x_zm_rhtaid=792"&gt;this IBA panel moderated by EyeWitness director Wendy Betts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical devices on the one hand are subject to damage within areas of conflict or harsh environments, and even when properly cared for, devices may be seized by authorities at military checkpoints or border crossings; resulting in evidence lost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Online, there are a multitude of challenges presented when trying to preserve digital evidence. Major ones are the automated flagging and deletions systems on platforms such as YouTube, Facebook, Twitter. Due to the often violent and graphic nature of pictures and videos uploaded from regions facing human-caused atrocities, original material containing potentially pertinent evidence may be automatically deleted, especially if the content is flagged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Content distributed online is also victim of targeted censorship, and link rot – the phenomenon associated with how the web decays over time as hyperlinks fail to point to their intended target and as remote resources become unresponsive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href="#admissibility-of-a-piece-of-evidence-is-not-always-a-given" id="admissibility-of-a-piece-of-evidence-is-not-always-a-given"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Admissibility of a piece of evidence is not always a given&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what distinguishes 'digital' evidence from any other form of evidence is that at its finest granularity it is composed of 'digits' — arrangements of ones and zeros. Despite the seemingly unbiased method of recording digital information as either True or False (either “1” or “0”), when presented in legal settings digital information is not guaranteed to be admissible evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the large volume of disinformation present online and the inherent ‘plasticity’ of digital information — that is, its ability to be altered, rewritten, or deleted — it is unsurprising that digital evidence is subject to great scrutiny during juridical processes. Needless to say, just because a picture or video depicts something does not guarantee it is authentic and any alternative to this thinking could give weight to potentially falsified evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to establishing the evidentiary value of a piece of evidence is respecting its ‘chain of custody’. In a &lt;a href="https://blog.witness.org/2020/04/making-your-metadata-matter-part-2/"&gt;two-part blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Wendy Betts and Raquel Vazquez Llorente (the Director and Senior Legal Advisor of eyeWitness to Atrocities, respectively) elaborate on  the importance of the chain of custody in legal proceedings, stating “the key to chain of custody is proving that the footage remains unchanged from the time it was captured. While this might not be always possible for human rights defenders, the metadata collected by a documentation app can help demonstrate chain of custody, but it needs to meet some conditions. The key concepts here are when was the metadata captured, and who potentially had the ability to alter it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Betts and Vazquez Llorente’s post, they touch on two critical points related to digital evidence preservation. The first is that establishing chain of custody serves to authenticate evidence by establishing its original source, digital-pathway of movement and the absence of opportunities for this information to be altered — effectively, acting similarly to an ‘alibi’. The second is the importance of preserving the necessary metadata, which ties the now authenticated evidence to a time and place, thus giving the material its necessary contextual and legal relevance as evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For context, EyeWitness' lead product, a documentation app handles this problem at the source by offering a camera mode, thus starting the chain of custody claim from the moment of capture – whereas the Digital Evidence Toolkit deals with research material collected after-the-fact)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early example of digital evidence preservation which is helpful in conceptualising digital  ‘chain of custody’ was the process of procuring evidence during the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY), where digital information whether it be data from a computer hard drive or digital photography was treated as if it were analog to ensure the proper handling of evidence. In Susan Schuppli’s &lt;a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/material-witness"&gt;‘Material Witness’&lt;/a&gt;, she writes “a series of images taken or produced with a digital camera by an OTP (Office of the Prosecutor) investigator in the aftermath of a war crime would be burned to disk, the CD carrying these images photographed and labeled, the image of this CD carrying the images taken at the crime scene filed with the Tribunals’ Registry and given a unique number.” While this method of evidence procurement was more suited to the period, in principle the same process can be applied to digital evidence today where a unique number is assigned to the evidence once its chain of custody is established and the evidence is in an immutable state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where in the past a burned-CD labelled with a unique number would suffice, nowadays the sheer volume of data coming out of mass atrocity crimes in some places makes this particular solution, er, unpractical. To say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;← Back to homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="280" scrolling="no" src="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.substack.com/embed" width="100%"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;footer class="mw6-l mw100-ns center bt"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the generous funding and support of&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="flex"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-bmbf.svg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-okfn.svg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Basile Simon</name></author></entry><entry><id>urn:uuid:fde2ac20-e857-43cd-9a09-e62ad31351d4</id><title>Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?</title><link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-1.html" type="text/html" title="Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-10T00:00:00Z</published><updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00Z</updated><content type="html" xml:base="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-1.html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;&lt;head&gt;&lt;meta charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;meta content="IE=edge,chrome=1" http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible"&gt;&lt;meta content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0, user-scalable=no" name="viewport"&gt;&lt;link href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Roboto:400,700" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/favicon.png" rel="icon" type="image/png"&gt;&lt;title&gt;Digital Evidence Toolkit&lt;/title&gt;&lt;link href="site.main.css" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css"&gt;&lt;/head&gt;&lt;body class="w-80 mw100-ns mw6-l center pv5"&gt;&lt;header&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;&lt;h1 class="f3-s f3-m f3-l tc lh-title mt0 mb4"&gt;The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/header&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a href="#newsletter-1-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved" id="newsletter-1-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I'd love your help&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn't admissible within court because it was improperly' handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the complete absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived - future prosecution efforts continue to remain in jeopardy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether you practice journalism, law, or advocate within civil society, the entanglement of digital technology and our physical environment has become commonplace. While more accessible forms of technology have given civilians the tools to readily record media and data — that has the 'potential' to be admissible evidence in court — the absence of any standardised legal frameworks regarding how data should be collected and stored presents a very important and contemporary problem: &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do we forensically handle digital evidence?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) is a project bringing together expert voices from the field to talk about the complexities of handling digital evidence. It aims to create a robust, immutable archiving software. Designed to preserve the digital chain of custody to a high enough standard to sustain the intense juridical pressure and scrutiny presented by state-actors or multi-national corporations. Raising the bar of what a group of dedicated individuals can do to protect the material they collect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is currently in development and frankly there is so much to read and know that we'd love to hear from you. Please reach out to &lt;a href="&amp;#109;a&amp;#105;&amp;#x6c;&amp;#x74;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#x3a;&amp;#98;&amp;#x61;&amp;#x73;i&amp;#108;&amp;#x65;&amp;#64;d&amp;#105;&amp;#103;&amp;#105;t&amp;#97;l&amp;#x65;&amp;#118;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x64;&amp;#101;&amp;#110;c&amp;#x65;&amp;#x74;o&amp;#111;&amp;#x6c;&amp;#x6b;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#46;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#x67;"&gt;&amp;#x62;&amp;#97;&amp;#115;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#x65;&amp;#64;&amp;#100;&amp;#105;&amp;#x67;&amp;#105;&amp;#116;&amp;#x61;&amp;#108;&amp;#x65;&amp;#x76;&amp;#x69;&amp;#x64;&amp;#101;&amp;#x6e;&amp;#99;&amp;#101;t&amp;#111;&amp;#x6f;&amp;#x6c;k&amp;#x69;&amp;#116;&amp;#46;&amp;#111;&amp;#x72;&amp;#103;&lt;/a&gt; 👋&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(or join this newsletter for more)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;section&gt;&lt;a class="nodeco" href="/"&gt;← Back to homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="280" scrolling="no" src="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.substack.com/embed" width="100%"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/section&gt;&lt;footer class="mw6-l mw100-ns center bt"&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the generous funding and support of&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="flex"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-bmbf.svg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://prototypefund.de/wp-content/uploads/2016/07/logo-okfn.svg"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content><author><name>Basile Simon</name></author></entry></feed>