<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/</link><description>Recent content on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Copyright © 2021-25, Basile Simon</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Coming Soon: Digital Evidence Toolkit x Microsoft Relativity</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/microsoft-relativity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/microsoft-relativity/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seamlessly integrate Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) into Microsoft Relativity, bringing powerful evidence validation, metadata analysis, secure archiving, and chain-of-custody tracking directly into your legal workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This integration enhances eDiscovery, compliance, and digital forensics, allowing law firms, investigators, and litigation teams to verify, preserve, and present digital evidence with unmatched security and integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="what-to-expect">What to Expect&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Automated Metadata Validation&lt;/strong> – Detect inconsistencies and verify authenticity within Relativity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Chain of Custody Tracking&lt;/strong> – Ensure tamper-proof documentation from collection to courtroom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Secure Archiving –&lt;/strong> Store digital evidence with cryptographic verification for long-term integrity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Court-Ready Exports&lt;/strong> – Generate legally admissible reports within Relativity’s case management system.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Of High Interest? Be in Touch&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Turn WordPress into a Powerful Evidence Management Platform</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/wordpress-plugin/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/wordpress-plugin/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) WordPress Plugin transforms WordPress into a secure, verifiable evidence management system, allowing teams to capture, authenticate, and manage digital content with built-in chain-of-custody tracking and court-ready exports. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re an investigative journalist, a legal professional, or a compliance officer, our plugin ensures that every piece of digital evidence is verifiable and tamper-proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="key-features">Key Features:&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Metadata Analysis&lt;/strong> – Automatically extract, verify, and log key metadata for every uploaded file.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Content Credentials Integration&lt;/strong> – Display cryptographic proof of authenticity and authorship using Content Credentials technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Chain of Custody Tracking&lt;/strong> – Ensure secure, tamper-proof documentation of every change, action, and transfer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Court-Ready Exports&lt;/strong> – Generate reports in legally admissible formats with a verifiable audit trail.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Seamless WordPress Integration&lt;/strong> – Works with existing media libraries, post types, and workflows.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="how-it-works">How It Works&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Built with PHP and JavaScript, the DEPT WordPress Plugin seamlessly integrates with your WordPress media library and enables automatic metadata analysis upon file upload. Using SHA-256 hashing and a tamper-proof ledger database (QLDB or alternative immutable storage), each file’s authenticity is recorded and tracked.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Archive Webpages with Proof of Integrity</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/webpage-archiving/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/webpage-archiving/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) offers a seamless way to capture and authenticate web content while ensuring a verifiable chain of custody. Our one-click browser extension allows you to archive webpages with cryptographic proof, making them admissible in legal, journalistic, and research contexts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every saved webpage is stored alongside metadata, DNS records, and a tamper-proof ledger entry, ensuring long-term integrity. Whether you’re investigating misinformation, documenting critical online evidence, or preserving web pages for compliance, our solution guarantees authenticity you can trust.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Support for S3-class cloud storage</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage/</guid><description>&lt;p>For relatively obvious reasons, we are working towards supporting teams and groups who wish to contribute to a single, collective repository of archived material.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first step in this direction is to open up the data storage options, so archived records can be browsed by several people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>We’ve just released &lt;a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit/deptoolkit/releases">the Toolkit v.0.11.0&lt;/a> which now supports S3-class cloud storage as both a destination and a source – in plain English, the Toolkit can now replicate its archives to the cloud and serve data from it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Original DEPToolkit prototype</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/original-dept-prototype/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/original-dept-prototype/</guid><description>&lt;p>Welcome to the documentation of the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit, a one-click tool to archive and annotate webpages while demonstrating chain of custody throughout. The Toolkit is a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With only one click of the mouse, the material will be &lt;strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>stored durably&lt;/strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to &lt;strong>go back to search through&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>annotate the material&lt;/strong>, and to &lt;strong>export working copies&lt;/strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>End of grant announcement: the Toolkit is now MVP!</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp/</guid><description>&lt;p>The DEPToolkit is a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With only one click of the mouse, the material will be &lt;strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>stored durably&lt;/strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to &lt;strong>go back to search through&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>annotate the material&lt;/strong>, and to &lt;strong>export working copies&lt;/strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A database built thusly can be handed to a prosecutor ten years down the line, and they will be able to say with mathematical certainty: &lt;strong>“the material in this archive is identical and contemporary to the one saved at the time, ten years ago.”&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Addressing the Berkeley protocol</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol/</guid><description>&lt;p>The leading light in terms of what we&amp;rsquo;re shooting for is the &lt;strong>Berkeley Protocol on Digital Open Source Investigations.&lt;/strong> The &lt;em>Protocol&lt;/em> defines an adequate preservation as respecting certain criteria.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Here&amp;rsquo;s how the Digital Evidence Toolkit follows these guidelines:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="authenticity">Authenticity&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;A digital item remains unchanged from when it was collected&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Toolkit preserves content and authenticity proofs (SHA256 hashes of all files and bundles, a U.S. federal standard) separately and implements both the verification of an item and the lookup of a collection of items in the archive.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Newsletter #4: Time(stamped), Time(lapsed)</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed/</guid><description>&lt;p>Time. Dates. Data points in the legal battle over the value of pieces of evidence. But are they really this hard, indisputable and demonstrable?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Metadata is supposed to &lt;em>describe&lt;/em> a digital medium – the word comes from &lt;em>meta: “referring to itself, or to something of its own type,”&lt;/em> reads the Cambridge Dictionary. Think of the date at which a picture was taken, the model of scanner used to digitise a piece of paper, a location somewhere on the planet added by the uploader of a video, as well as its description&amp;hellip;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence/</guid><description>&lt;p>_(In case you missed it last week, the previous issue of this newsletter, “Wait, digital evidence?” in which we touch on chain of custody and admissibility, &lt;a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-2.html">can be found here&lt;/a>)__&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>It&amp;rsquo;s maybe time to clarify a few things about what the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit is and does*&lt;/strong>, from the two original thoughts:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Content living online is at risk&lt;/strong>. Deletion, link rot, censorship, accidental destruction – you name it. The social internet may be great at surfacing and disseminating information but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty terrible at preserving it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>If the goal is prosecution, the standards of research, due diligence and safekeeping are a different ballpark to those of journalistic publication&lt;/strong>. As a journalist, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen first-hand how some of this evidence is weighed and cleared by Legal. As co-founder of Airwars, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen first-hand the steps we took to ensure our material wouldn&amp;rsquo;t disappear. If my law studies serve me well: both the above fall short of what the courts demand when it comes to evidentiary standards.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>We aim to provide a &lt;strong>proof-of-concept software&lt;/strong> for researchers and small teams sifting through online material. With only one click of the mouse, the material will be &lt;strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody and stored durably&lt;/strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to go back to &lt;strong>search through and annotate&lt;/strong> the material, and to &lt;strong>export working copies&lt;/strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It would be difficult to explain our ambitions for the Digital Evidence Toolkit without first defining ‘digital evidence,’ a term used to describe any information stored in a digital format that is related to any future or ongoing litigation. This evidence may be stored on physical devices (such as smartphones, computers, or hard drives), or transmitted on the internet.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&amp;rsquo;d love your help&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn&amp;rsquo;t admissible within court because it was improperly&amp;rsquo; handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the complete absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived - future prosecution efforts continue to remain in jeopardy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Toolkit started from a funded software grant, which enabled its main author, &lt;a href="https://basilesimon.fr">Basile Simon&lt;/a> to focus on these legal and technical issues he had encountered while at Airwars.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Presently based in Berlin, Basile is a multi-disciplinary researcher bridging between engineering, law, and journalism in promoting accountability for causing harm to civilians.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a fellow at Stanford Electrical Engineering, he is part of the &lt;a href="https://starlinglab.org">Starling Lab for Data Integrity&lt;/a> (Stanford/USC), and is a resident with the European Center for Constitutional and Human Rights (ECCHR) in the cross-NGO investigative group &lt;a href="https://investigative-commons.org/">Forensis&lt;/a>.&lt;br>
He co-founded &lt;a href="https://airwars.org">Airwars&lt;/a> in 2014 and worked for the BBC, Reuters, and The Times and The Sunday Times.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Getting Started</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="_its-not-you--its-me_">&lt;em>“It&amp;rsquo;s not you – it&amp;rsquo;s me”&lt;/em>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If the instructions in this guide feel a bit much, it&amp;rsquo;s likely because the Toolkit is still an alpha-version software which assumes a certain technical knowledge. There are technical solutions to simplifying this setup, but these were not prioritised.&lt;/p>
&lt;aside>
🙏 If this is something you have expertise with and are happy to help, do reach out at **basile@digitalevidencetoolkit.org**
&lt;/aside>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h2 id="setting-up-the-ledger">Setting up the ledger&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Toolkit requires a working connection with Amazon Web Services, and thus that you have some kind of well-permissioned account or IAM role.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>