<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>News on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news</link><author>Basile Simon</author><description>Latest updates, developments, and announcements from the Digital Evidence Toolkit project. Stay informed about new features, case studies, and advances in digital evidence preservation technology.</description><generator>Hugo 0.133.0</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Copyright 2021-2025 Basile Simon. Licensed under CC BY 4.0.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license><item><title>The German Evidentiary Paradox: Why Web Archives Might Fail in Civil Court</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/the-german-evidentiary-paradox-why-web-archives-might-fail-in-civil-court</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/the-german-evidentiary-paradox-why-web-archives-might-fail-in-civil-court/</guid><description>Discover why German civil law imposes stricter authentication on digital evidence than criminal proceedings. Learn how § 371a ZPO, qualified signatures, and mandatory e-filing determine if your web archives survive judicial scrutiny.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>German courts treat web archives with surprising sophistication – and surprising contradiction. Our newly compiled legal framework considers how civil proceedings demand stricter authentication than criminal cases, despite lower constitutional stakes. Notarised web captures receive presumptive authenticity<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, while screenshots face judicial skepticism regardless of reliability.</p>
<p>The framework maps a fragmented landscape where mandatory electronic filing since 2022<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> collides with authentication standards designed for analogue evidence. The Internet Archive gains approval for patent prior art<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> but rejection for contract enforcement. Professional archiving services with qualified timestamps trump simple screenshots. eIDAS harmonisation accelerates acceptance, yet authentication infrastructure remains essential – not optional.</p>
<p>For practitioners navigating Germany&rsquo;s §286 ZPO<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> free evaluation regime versus §371a ZPO&rsquo;s enhanced presumptions, this analysis decodes the authentication hierarchy determining whether digital evidence survives or fails. The dichotomy is stark: proper technical competence now separates winning arguments from malpractice liability.</p>
<p>This legal analysis is available exclusively by request. Please email at <a href="mailto:hi@digitalevidencetoolkit.org">hi@digitalevidencetoolkit.org</a>.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><em>Anscheinsbeweis</em> literally meaning &ldquo;prima facie evidence&rdquo;, §371a ZPO&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>§ 130d ZPO, effective Jan 2022&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p><em>Bundespatentgericht</em> (Federal Patent Court),February 18, 2021&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:4">
<p><em>Freie Beweiswürdigung</em>&#160;<a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>Discover why German civil law imposes stricter authentication on digital evidence than criminal proceedings. Learn how § 371a ZPO, qualified signatures, and mandatory e-filing determine if your web archives survive judicial scrutiny.</dc:description><dc:date>2025-11-18T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>The first submission to its kind to the ICC – and the future of the Toolkit</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/the-first-submission-to-its-kind-to-the-icc-and-the-future-of-the-toolkit</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/the-first-submission-to-its-kind-to-the-icc-and-the-future-of-the-toolkit/</guid><description>How cutting-edge digital evidence technology made history with the first blockchain-verified submission to the International Criminal Court</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>FA few things have happened since I announced v.0.11 of the Toolkit, in early March. Now is as good a time as any to take stock of where this newsletter/Substack publication will be headed.</p>
<p>First, I’m delighted to finally announce I’m now Director of Special Projects at Stanford/USC Starling Lab. That’s what the website blurb says about the Lab:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Starling Lab is an academic research lab innovating with the latest cryptographic methods and decentralized web protocols to meet the technical and ethical challenges of establishing trust in our most sensitive digital records.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="/images/starling-logo.webp" alt=""></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Starling uses open-source tools, best practices, and case studies to securely capture, store and verify digital content. With applications across news media, historical preservation and legal accountability, the potential use cases for the Starling Framework are numerous.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>The fit between the Toolkit and the Lab</strong> was obvious from our first conversations, and I look forward to continuing the research I started last year with the Toolkit under the umbrella of these prestigious institutions.</p>
<p>I feel a little vindicated to have found a group of folks who also think not only of this type of data, but also along the lines of demonstration of chain of custody (preserve integrity and prove all access, hello web3 tokens), self-identifiable and -addressable data (it’s called CID in Dweb world, apparently), and durable storage ideas (thanks to the deep experience building on decentralised web tech in the Lab).</p>
<hr>
<p>Second, top of my list of responsibilities right now is obviously Ukraine. At the weekend, <strong>we filed an official submission to the International Criminal Court’s Office of the Prosecutor</strong> and launched the <strong>Dokaz project</strong> (“proof,” in Ukrainian).</p>
<p>That legal submission was a joint effort between us, Hala Systems and the Atlantic Council’s DFRLab, and rests on a series of attacks against schools in Kharkiv, which took place in early March 2022. The crime we allege is the deliberate destruction of protected civilian objects, a crime disproportionately affecting children. This focus brings state-of-the-art tools to document crimes that are under-investigated and under-prosecuted in courts worldwide, against one of the world’s most vulnerable groups.</p>
<p>Last year, when I was developing the Toolkit, my coach Simon asked me what this project’s <em>North Star</em> was. “Hmm,” I thought, “I guess that this software should be used in a formal ICC submission. That’s a grand enough moonshot for me.”</p>
<p>Well, just a year later I feel I kept looking at this North Star, which guided my choice when things became real with Stanford. It’s not the Toolkit backing this submission – <strong>but I look up to the Starling Framework stack that my colleagues built as what the Toolkit could have been.</strong></p>
<p><strong>And I feel privileged to be in a position to participate to where it goes next</strong>.</p>
<p>CNN has all the details about how original this submission is: <a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2022/06/10/tech/ukraine-war-crimes-blockchain/index.html">Exclusive: A crypto-based dossier could help prove Russia committed war crimes</a></p>
<p>So, two messages:</p>
<p>One: 50% of the funds raised for this project are earmarked for Ukrainians, so here’s a request: if you’re an OSINT analysis, a researcher with legal chops, or an enfineer curious about the decentralised web – be in touch. basile at starling lab dot org.</p>
<p>Two: I’m not yet sure what will happen to the Toolkit and to this newsletter. I relied on my conversations with some of you so much to shape what I did that I’d like to hear from you again. As above: basile at starling lab dot org.</p>
<p>Until then, 👋</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>How cutting-edge digital evidence technology made history with the first blockchain-verified submission to the International Criminal Court</dc:description><dc:date>2022-06-13T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Support for S3-class cloud storage</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage/</guid><description>The Toolkit now supports S3 cloud storage, a first step towards collaboration</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For relatively obvious reasons, we are working towards supporting teams and groups who wish to contribute to a single, collective repository of archived material.</p>
<p>The first step in this direction is to open up the data storage options, so archived records can be browsed by several people.</p>
<p><strong>We’ve just released <a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit/deptoolkit/releases">the Toolkit v.0.11.0</a> which now supports S3-class cloud storage as both a destination and a source – in plain English, the Toolkit can now replicate its archives to the cloud and serve data from it.</strong></p>
<hr>
<p>There are still a number of things you can do to help:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you have experience with auth and auth-ing an existing product, please get in touch.</li>
<li>Incidentally, devops skills and docker-fu would make a big difference in helping to scope and shape a more collaborative offering.</li>
<li>We are always looking for folks to write unit and integration tests.</li>
</ul>
<p>Thank you – and stay safe.</p>
<hr>
<h4 id="useful-links">Useful links:</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.substack.com/">Newsletter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.notion.site/Getting-started-15521f4125534f4aa758a2575c27ad5c">Getting started</a> and <a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.notion.site/Technical-Journal-01ad0720aebc4f9c9a8036da0fd7426b">technical documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="/addressing-berkeley/">Addressing the criteria of the Berkeley Protocol</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit/deptoolkit/releases">Releases and changelog</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/orgs/digitalevidencetoolkit/projects/3">Roadmap board</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>The Toolkit now supports S3 cloud storage, a first step towards collaboration</dc:description><dc:date>2022-03-05T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Getting Started</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started/</guid><description>⚠️ Deprecation Warning: This guide references AWS QLDB, which will reach end of support on July 31, 2025. AWS is no longer accepting new QLDB users. Please contact us at hi@digitalevidencetoolkit.org for updated setup instructions using alternative immutable storage solutions.&amp;#xA;&amp;amp;ldquo;It&amp;amp;rsquo;s not you – it&amp;amp;rsquo;s me&amp;amp;rdquo; If the instructions in this guide feel a bit much, it&amp;amp;rsquo;s likely because the Toolkit is still an alpha-version software which assumes a certain technical knowledge.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p><strong>⚠️ Deprecation Warning:</strong> This guide references AWS QLDB, which will reach end of support on July 31, 2025. AWS is no longer accepting new QLDB users. Please contact us at <a href="mailto:hi@digitalevidencetoolkit.org">hi@digitalevidencetoolkit.org</a> for updated setup instructions using alternative immutable storage solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="_its-not-you--its-me_"><em>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s not you – it&rsquo;s me&rdquo;</em></h2>
<p>If the instructions in this guide feel a bit much, it&rsquo;s likely because the Toolkit is still an alpha-version software which assumes a certain technical knowledge. There are technical solutions to simplifying this setup, but these were not prioritised.</p>
<aside>
🙏 If this is something you have expertise with and are happy to help, do reach out at **basile@digitalevidencetoolkit.org**
</aside>
<hr>
<h2 id="setting-up-the-ledger">Setting up the ledger</h2>
<p>The Toolkit requires a working connection with Amazon Web Services, and thus that you have some kind of well-permissioned account or IAM role.</p>
<p>In short, you will need:</p>
<ol>
<li>the AWS CLI and an authorised profile in <code>~/.aws/credentials</code> (see <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/cli/latest/userguide/install-cliv2.html">“Installing the AWS CLI v2”</a> - <em>docs.aws.amazon.com)</em></li>
<li>an existing QLDB ledger, with a blank table in it (see <a href="https://qldbguide.com/docs/guide/getting-started/#using-aws-console">“Creating a QLDB ledger from the AWS Console”</a> - <em>qldbguide.com</em>)</li>
</ol>
<p>Not required but recommended is an S3 bucket in which to store Toolkit data.</p>
<p><strong>Remember the names</strong> of the ledger and of its table. You&rsquo;ll need them shortly (see &ldquo;Environment&rdquo; below).</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="environment">Environment</h2>
<p>After cloning the repository, create an <code>.env</code> file at the root or copy <code>.env.example</code>. The job of this file is to contain variables you really don&rsquo;t want to share publicly, so keep this out of version control software.</p>
<p>This file <strong>must contain:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>AWS access credentials and preferred region</li>
<li>Details about the ledger and S3 bucket</li>
</ul>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;your aws access key&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;your aws secret key&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>AWS_REGION<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;eu-central-1 (or another region)&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>BUCKET_NAME<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;anS3BucketName&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>LEDGER_NAME<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;yourLedgerName&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>DOC_TABLE_NAME<span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;yourTableName&#34;</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><hr>
<h2 id="recommended-way-of-running-the-toolkit">Recommended way of running the Toolkit</h2>
<aside>
💡 At the very least, **you will need Docker installed on your system.
    •** https://docs.docker.com/get-docker/
</aside>
<p>The Docker Compose orchestration is composed of several services:</p>
<ol>
<li>An Express/TypeScript API</li>
<li>A plain JS browser extension</li>
<li>And a frontend</li>
</ol>
<p>To start the whole app:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ docker-compose up
</span></span></code></pre></div><hr>
<h2 id="running-without-docker">Running without Docker</h2>
<p>Ensure you&rsquo;re running <code>node &gt; 10.0</code> — the recommended version is the LTS, i.e. <code>node v16</code>. If you are using <code>nvm</code>:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ nvm use --lts
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&gt; Now using node v16.13.0
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Manually install dependencies for each service:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ cd ui/ &amp; npm install
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ cd extension/ &amp; npm install
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ npm install
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Then use the npm script including all services:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ npm run all
</span></span></code></pre></div><hr>
<h2 id="storage-options">Storage options</h2>
<p>By including a bucket in the <code>.env</code> config, you’re choosing to replicate your archival on S3.</p>
<p>Namely, the Store (<code>src/store/index.ts</code>) will:</p>
<ul>
<li>upon receiving an archive request, store the Bundle files both locally and on S3,</li>
<li>and upon receiving a file request (e.g. the UI fetching thumbnails), serve it from S3.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="is-there-anybody-out-there">Is there anybody out there?</h2>
<h3 id="api-and-frontend">API and frontend</h3>
<p>The API should be available at <a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit/deptoolkit/releases">http://localhost:3000</a> — assert this by running:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ curl http://localhost:3000/list-docs
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&gt; <span style="color:#f92672">[</span> <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>...<span style="color:#f92672">}</span>, <span style="color:#f92672">{</span>...<span style="color:#f92672">}</span> <span style="color:#f92672">]</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The UI should be available at http://localhost:8000 in your web browser of choice. API requests are proxied through the UI. Thus, the following queries are equivalent:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ curl http://localhost:3000/list-docs        // as before
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>$ curl http://localhost:8000/api/list-docs
</span></span></code></pre></div><h3 id="browser-extension">Browser extension</h3>
<p>The extension should be being bundled on your filesystem. Pop open your browser&rsquo;s extension runtime by pasting this in the URL bar:</p>
<p><code>about:debugging#/runtime/this-firefox</code></p>
<p>Click <em>“Load temporary Add-on&hellip;”</em> and navigate to <code>extension/addon</code> to select <code>manifest.json</code>.</p>
<p>The extension should have been loaded in your extension bar, as shown below:</p>
<p><img src="/static/images/dept-untitled.png" alt="Untitled"></p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:date>2022-01-01T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>End of grant announcement: the Toolkit is now MVP!</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp/</guid><description>The Toolkit enters beta software status. Here&amp;#39;s how we&amp;#39;ll be moving forward.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The DEPToolkit is a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material.</p>
<p>With only one click of the mouse, the material will be <strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody</strong> and <strong>stored durably</strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to <strong>go back to search through</strong> and <strong>annotate the material</strong>, and to <strong>export working copies</strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.</p>
<p>A database built thusly can be handed to a prosecutor ten years down the line, and they will be able to say with mathematical certainty: <strong>“the material in this archive is identical and contemporary to the one saved at the time, ten years ago.”</strong></p>
<h2 id="problem-definition">Problem definition</h2>
<p>What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn&rsquo;t admissible in court because it had been improperly handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived – future prosecution efforts remain in jeopardy.</p>
<p>As a journalist, I&rsquo;ve seen first-hand how some of this evidence is weighed and cleared by legal departments. As co-founder of Airwars, a monitoring NGO, I&rsquo;ve seen first-hand the steps we took to ensure our material wouldn&rsquo;t disappear. And if my law studies serve me well: both the above fall short of what the courts may demand when it comes to evidentiary standards.</p>
<h2 id="enter-the-toolkit">Enter, the Toolkit</h2>
<p>We want this to be the plastic sealed bag in which evidence is deposited, and which is then kept under watch in an evidence room, where each access is tracked and reported in a log.</p>
<p>Our Toolkit does several things:</p>
<h3 id="one-click-to-preserve">One click to preserve:</h3>
<p>The Toolkit offers a one-click research tool preserving digital evidence through the web browser. The one-button browser extension delivers content to the self-hosted micro-service. No waiting, no series of things to click on. More time spent researching.</p>
<p><img src="/images/illustrations/1.svg" alt="Architecture diagram"></p>
<h3 id="future-proof-archives-and-authenticity-proof">Future-proof archives and authenticity proof:</h3>
<p>The Toolkit preserves a copy of the material <em>as well as</em> the proof of its authenticity. Future-proof offline copies are created, and their digital signatures immediately added to a remote immutable ledger. All the material is identified by SHA256, a U.S. federal government cryptography standard.</p>
<p><img src="/images/illustrations/2.svg" alt="Architecture diagram"></p>
<h3 id="your-archive-is-yours-browse-annotate-export">Your archive is yours: browse, annotate, export:</h3>
<p>The Toolkit facilitates browsing the archive thus created, its annotation and metadata enrichment, as well as the export of working copies. All access and additions are added to the immutable log, accounted for, and replayable at will.</p>
<p><img src="/images/illustrations/3.svg" alt="Architecture diagram"></p>
<h3 id="lookup-and-prove-reverse-verification-of-the-custody">Lookup-and-prove: reverse verification of the custody</h3>
<p>The Toolkit provides a “lookup-and-prove” mechanism demonstrating proper chain of custody of the material, for the case where a trove of documents has to be cross-checked against the Toolkit&rsquo;s proof mechanisms.</p>
<p><img src="/images/illustrations/4.svg" alt="Architecture diagram"></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="benefits">Benefits</h2>
<p>Our challenge with the Toolkit is <strong>to preserve a piece of evidence from the moment it reaches us.</strong> We&rsquo;re dealing with after-the-fact research, as opposed to that coming straight from the field (see for example <a href="https://www.eyewitness.global">EyeWitness</a>), a star-project proposing an end-to-end, camera-to-courtroom workflow).</p>
<p>As I wrote before:</p>
<p>“<strong>*The Toolkit only addresses provenance and chain the custody from the moment of record.</strong> The content stored very well may be unauthentic, doctored, or fake – but with the Toolkit, it will be adequately preserved.”*</p>
<p>There are several implications in terms of metadata:</p>
<ul>
<li>In addition to <strong>future-proof archives of webpages and screenshots</strong>, we&rsquo;re capturing <strong>some metadata</strong> about pages and asking users about their potential needs beyond the
obvious (think Google Analytics tracking codes, DNS records, etc.)</li>
<li>This metadata is preserved and their unique signatures notarised in the <strong>immutable ledger</strong> we are using. This means that <strong>once written in the database, there is no lossy change possible</strong> aside from a complete deletion. Once again: we&rsquo;re addressing chain of custody <em>from the moment of record</em> only.</li>
<li>The centralised, Amazon Web Services-run ledger provides a hybrid method of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trusted_timestamping">trusted timestamping</a> as per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ANSI_ASC_X9.95_Standard">ANSI ASC X9.95</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO/IEC_18014">ISO/IEC 18014</a>: each insertion in and revision of the ledger has a timestamp, er, <em>stamped</em> on it by Amazon. It&rsquo;s a feature, not a bug – and a highly desirable one with that.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re now able to verifiably demonstrate appropriate custody of an archived</strong> webpage from a point in time which could not have been faked.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="going-forward"><strong>Going forward</strong></h2>
<p>We&rsquo;re working on a number of partnerships that aim to validate some of our assumptions.</p>
<p>From initial user interviews and contact with practitioners, we&rsquo;ll now be working on two parallel tracks: the collaboration on collective datasets/cases, and the interoperability with other document management systems.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;ll be offering assistance to pro bono law firms and vulnerable groups, including single victims self-documenting their troubles.</p>
<h2 id="useful-links"><strong>Useful links</strong></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.substack.com/">Newsletter</a></li>
<li><a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.notion.site/Getting-started-15521f4125534f4aa758a2575c27ad5c">Getting started</a> and <a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.notion.site/Technical-Journal-01ad0720aebc4f9c9a8036da0fd7426b">technical documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="/addressing-berkeley/">Addressing the criteria of the Berkeley Protocol</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit/deptoolkit/releases">Releases and changelog</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/orgs/digitalevidencetoolkit/projects/3">Roadmap board</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>The Toolkit enters beta software status. Here&amp;#39;s how we&amp;#39;ll be moving forward.</dc:description><dc:date>2021-08-31T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Addressing the Berkeley protocol</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol/</guid><description>How the Toolkit fares with regards to the Berkeley Protocol&amp;#39;s criteria</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The leading light in terms of what we&rsquo;re shooting for is the <strong>Berkeley Protocol on Digital Open Source Investigations.</strong> The <em>Protocol</em> defines an adequate preservation as respecting certain criteria.</p>
<p><strong>Here&rsquo;s how the Digital Evidence Toolkit follows these guidelines:</strong></p>
<hr>
<h3 id="authenticity">Authenticity</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;A digital item remains unchanged from when it was collected&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>The Toolkit preserves content and authenticity proofs (SHA256 hashes of all files and bundles, a U.S. federal standard) separately and implements both the verification of an item and the lookup of a collection of items in the archive.</p>
<h3 id="availability">Availability</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The continual existence and retrievability&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>The Toolkit ships with an example user interface implementing methods to retrieve and display content. See below: Renderability.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="identity">Identity</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The identifiability and distinguishability from other items&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>All records are identified by the sum of their parts, as well as by their position in the chain of records, such as each identifier is unique.</p>
<h3 id="persistence">Persistence</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The integrity and viability: the bit sequences must be intact&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>The Toolkit never edits the original files but constantly relies on their identity: their bit sequence (see hashing above, in Authenticity).</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="renderability">Renderability</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The ability of humans or machines to use or interact with a digital item&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>In addition to implementing a user interface demonstrating its programmatic equivalent, the file formats chosen by the Toolkit have been around for more than 25 years and protected by the W3C, a standards organisation.</p>
<h3 id="understandability">Understandability</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The ability to interpret and understand a digital item&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>The Toolkit captures items as they were understood by the researcher/case builder, and exposes them to the user again.</p>
<hr>
<p>A number of investigation-specific issues are also noted by the <em>Protocol</em> and are at the heart of the Toolkit, driving its features:</p>
<h3 id="chain-of-custody">Chain of custody</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;The chronological documentation of the sequence of custodians of a piece of information or evidence&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>By leveraging the ledger technology, the Toolkit implements a perfect log of everything that happens to the archive as it grows. The resulting log is immutable and as an implementation of a Merkle Tree, further intertwines each record&rsquo;s history with others&rsquo; in the chain.</p>
<h3 id="evidentiary-and-working-copies">Evidentiary and Working copies</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;A working copy should be created and stored separately so that investigators can work with the copy, rather than the original. Any and all changes to the item, including the making of copies, should be documented&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>While accessing the originals manually is possible, the Toolkit and its user interface both implement the generation of working copies, on request. Automatic creation at the moment of addition to the archive is also possible. All changes can be documented in the ledger – see above: Chain of custody.</p>
<h3 id="storage">Storage</h3>
<p><strong>&ldquo;Helps ensure the persistence of digital items and the ability to find and retrieve them&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>The Toolkit is built as a general-purpose solution where file management can be accomplished in different, from sensitive investigations conducted on one machine to full storage in the cloud from the point of record. We aim to leverage cloud technology and multiple duplication across data-centres to increase the reliability of the access to the originals.</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>How the Toolkit fares with regards to the Berkeley Protocol&amp;#39;s criteria</dc:description><dc:date>2021-08-25T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Newsletter #4: Time(stamped), Time(lapsed)</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed/</guid><description>Dealing with metadata and timestamping with an immutable ledger</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Time. Dates. Data points in the legal battle over the value of pieces of evidence. But are they really this hard, indisputable and demonstrable?</p>
<p>Metadata is supposed to <em>describe</em> a digital medium – the word comes from <em>meta: “referring to itself, or to something of its own type,”</em> reads the Cambridge Dictionary. Think of the date at which a picture was taken, the model of scanner used to digitise a piece of paper, a location somewhere on the planet added by the uploader of a video, as well as its description&hellip;</p>
<p>But while we&rsquo;re only at the beginning of media fudgery (see audio and video “deep fakes”, which are computationally expensive), editing metadata is often only a few clicks away and not well protected.</p>
<p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit places metadata at its core, and answers the question: what did a piece of evidence look like at a particular time? <strong>Both the content and the timestamp of record are cryptographically set in stone</strong>, so to speak.</p>
<p>During international prosecution efforts, there is often a <strong>considerable amount of time</strong> between the date of the alleged crimes and the trial of the accused. <a href="https://www.ejiltalk.org/part-i-what-can-be-done-about-the-length-of-proceedings-at-the-icc/">This period of time between crime and conviction</a> has amounted to 12 years in the Sierra Leone Tribunal, 24 years in the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY), and 30 years in the Nyiramasuhuko et al trial (encompassing the trials, convictions, and appeals process).</p>
<p><strong>With the Toolkit, I can claim “I recorded this information at this date” and I can prove that what I am showing you today is identical to what was recorded at the time.</strong></p>
<hr>
<h3 id="open-source-information"><strong>Open Source Information</strong></h3>
<p><strong>Digital media collected from online platforms</strong> is one kind of the digital, open source evidence types that have begun to play an increasingly large role in recent ad hoc tribunals.</p>
<p>In early cases such as Prosecutor v. Karemera (2012) and Prosecutor v. Bagosora (2008) video evidence pertaining to the crimes of the accused were corroborated by so-called “external indicators” <a href="https://journals.sas.ac.uk/deeslr/article/view/2130">in the form of transcripts and witness testimony.</a> <strong>In the absence of internal indicators, such as timestamps and other forms of metadata,</strong> prosecution efforts have successfully relied on external indicators, such as testimony or source identity information, to authenticate digital evidence. For instance, in the case against Karemara, transcripts of radio broadcasts were used <a href="https://journals.sas.ac.uk/deeslr/article/view/2130">to authenticate the date of a video that did not contain timestamped metadata.</a></p>
<h3 id="prosecutor-v-bemba"><strong>Prosecutor v. Bemba</strong></h3>
<p>The trial of Jean-Pierre Bemba Bongo (2015) set an <strong>important precedent for proper digital evidence collection</strong> following its intense scrutiny by the Defence team. The Prosecution submitted screenshots of Facebook photos alleged to show two corrupted witnesses together as indirect evidence of witness tampering, and while the screenshots alone were not evidence of the accusation, taken together with documents detailing a wire transfer from Bemba’s sister to one of witnesses depicted in the screenshot indicated <a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/forum/open-source-evidence-on-trial"><strong>the screenshots had the potential to gain probative value</strong></a>.</p>
<p>In response to this submission of evidence, the Defence contended that the screenshots should not be given any consideration because <a href="https://www.yalelawjournal.org/forum/open-source-evidence-on-trial">“it is impossible to know who posted the photos, when they were taken, where they were taken, who took them, or even if the people in the photos are who the prosecution claims they are.”</a> Moreover, the Defence also criticised the Prosecution’s <strong>crude extraction of the photos from Facebook in the form of screenshots, devoid of any metadata that could determine important qualities such as time, geographic location, or author.</strong></p>
<p>In the case of Prosecutor v. Bemba, <strong>the ICC ruling did not directly address the admissibility or probative value of the Facebook photos</strong> because the relationship between the two individuals was further substantiated by the introduction of witness testimony. ****But the dispute over the authenticity of these Facebook screenshots **highlights the importance of best practice when collecting digital evidence**. In subsequent trials, such as the case against Ahmad Al-Faqi Al-Mahdi, having learned from the Defence’s trivialisation of open source evidence during Bemba, <a href="https://lup.lub.lu.se/student-papers/search/publication/9048327">the Prosecution took preemptive steps</a> to geolocate videos “depicting the accused engaged in destroying mosques, overseeing and ordering others to destroy mosques as well as explaining his intent to destroy mosques.” Through their efforts, they were able to <a href="https://lup.lub.lu.se/student-papers/search/publication/9048327">establish probable dates and locations</a> of the incidents by identifying “multiple points of corroboration” seen in the videos.</p>
<p>The trial of Jean-Pierre Bemba Gombo is one of several instances (see <a href="https://lup.lub.lu.se/student-papers/search/publication/9048327">Karemara, Tolomir, Katanga and Ngudjolo Chui</a>) when <strong>ad hoc tribunals have demonstrated a relaxed attitude towards the admissibility of digital evidence</strong>. In the absence of metadata such as timestamps, GPS location, or authorship/IP-addresses, digital evidence has often been tied to supplementary forms of evidence such as testimony, where the weight it holds is only as strong as the credibility of the evidence it is tied to.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="then-trusted-timestamps">Then: trusted timestamps</h2>
<p>Our challenge with the Toolkit is <strong>to preserve a piece of evidence from the moment it reaches us.</strong> We&rsquo;re dealing with after-the-fact research, as opposed to that coming straight from the field (see for example <a href="%5Bhttps://www.eyewitness.global/%5D(https://www.eyewitness.global/)">EyeWitness</a>, a star-project proposing an end-to-end, camera-to-courtroom workflow).</p>
<p>As I wrote before:</p>
<p>“<strong>*The Toolkit only addresses provenance and chain the custody from the moment of record.</strong> The content stored very well may be unauthentic, doctored, or fake – but with the Toolkit, it will be adequately preserved.”*</p>
<p>There are several implications in terms of metadata:</p>
<ul>
<li>In addition to <strong>future-proof archives of webpages and screenshots</strong>, we&rsquo;re capturing <strong>some metadata</strong> about pages and asking users about their potential needs beyond the obvious (think Google Analytics tracking codes, DNS records, etc.)</li>
<li>This metadata is preserved and their unique signatures notarised in the <strong>immutable ledger</strong> we are using. This means that <strong>once written in the database, there is no lossy change possible</strong> aside from a complete deletion. Once again: we&rsquo;re addressing chain of custody <em>from the moment of record</em> only.</li>
<li>The centralised, Amazon Web Services-run ledger provides a hybrid method of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trusted_timestamping">trusted timestamping</a> as per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ANSI_ASC_X9.95_Standard">ANSI ASC X9.95</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO/IEC_18014">ISO/IEC 18014</a>: each insertion in and revision of the ledger has a timestamp, er, <em>stamped</em> on it by Amazon. It&rsquo;s a feature, not a bug – and a highly desirable one with that.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>We&rsquo;re now able to verifiably demonstrate appropriate custody of an archived webpage from a point in time which could not have been faked.</strong></p>
<p>More on authenticity and preservation of the files themselves later.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="updates">Updates</h2>
<p>We&rsquo;ve had lots of excellent conversations and user interviews, notably with ECCHR, the Bureau of Investigative Journalism, the UN, Harvard, and Bellingcat.</p>
<p>The grant period ends in a couple of weeks and I&rsquo;m now working on graphics, visuals and designs to share in future newsletter to better explain the choices and claims of the project.</p>
<p>I hope you&rsquo;ll stay tuned&hellip; don&rsquo;t hesitate to forward this email or share the newsletter!</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>Dealing with metadata and timestamping with an immutable ledger</dc:description><dc:date>2021-08-12T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence/</guid><description>We aim to provide a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material, which demonstrates chain of custody and durable preservation.</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>_(In case you missed it last week, the previous issue of this newsletter, “Wait, digital evidence?” in which we touch on chain of custody and admissibility, <a href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/newsletter-2.html">can be found here</a>)__</p>
<p><strong>It&rsquo;s maybe time to clarify a few things about what the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit is and does*</strong>, from the two original thoughts:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Content living online is at risk</strong>. Deletion, link rot, censorship, accidental destruction – you name it. The social internet may be great at surfacing and disseminating information but it&rsquo;s pretty terrible at preserving it.</li>
<li><strong>If the goal is prosecution, the standards of research, due diligence and safekeeping are a different ballpark to those of journalistic publication</strong>. As a journalist, I&rsquo;ve seen first-hand how some of this evidence is weighed and cleared by Legal. As co-founder of Airwars, I&rsquo;ve seen first-hand the steps we took to ensure our material wouldn&rsquo;t disappear. If my law studies serve me well: both the above fall short of what the courts demand when it comes to evidentiary standards.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>We aim to provide a <strong>proof-of-concept software</strong> for researchers and small teams sifting through online material. With only one click of the mouse, the material will be <strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody and stored durably</strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to go back to <strong>search through and annotate</strong> the material, and to <strong>export working copies</strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.</p>
<p>The central claim: a database built thusly can be handed to a prosecutor ten years down the line, and they will be able to say with mathematical certainty: <strong>“the material in this archive is identical and contemporary to the one saved at the time, ten years ago.”</strong></p>
<p>We want this to be the plastic sealed bag in which evidence is deposited, and which is then kept under watch in an evidence room, where each access is tracked and reported in a log.</p>
<hr>
<p>That’s not saying we solved the verification and authenticity questions – quite the contrary.</p>
<p>The Toolkit only addresses provenance and chain the custody from the moment of record. The content stored very well may be unauthentic, doctored, or fake – but with the Toolkit, it will be adequately preserved.</p>
<p><strong>And without this preservation, the court won’t have the chance to examine it and to sort the fake from the truthful.</strong></p>
<hr>
<h3 id="follow-along">Follow along</h3>
<p>The technical work is taking place <a href="https://github.com/digitalevidencetoolkit">on GitHub</a> and is best followed through <a href="https://github.com/orgs/digitalevidencetoolkit/projects/2">the Kanban board</a> tracking my progress in delivering a minimum viable product in the next couple of weeks.</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;ve got technical chops and have some spare time in the coming month, please get in touch. I&rsquo;m looking for reviewers, testers, TypeScript connoisseurs, and browser APIs experts.</p>
<h3 id="updates">Updates</h3>
<p>We&rsquo;ve reached out to the Centre for Information Resilience&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.info-res.org/myanmarwitness">Myanmar Witness project</a>. It&rsquo;s funded through the UK&rsquo;s Foreign, Commonwealth &amp; Development Office and claim: “All data is independently verified, hashed, and kept safely and securely.”</p>
<p>There&rsquo;s a new Berlin venture called <a href="https://www.berlinartlink.com/2021/06/25/forensic-architecture-investigative-commons-at-hkw">Investigative Commons</a>. The group, composed of <a href="https://mnemonic.org/en/about/">Mnemonic</a>, <a href="https://www.bellingcat.com/about/">Bellingcat</a>, <a href="https://forensic-architecture.org/about/agency">Forensic Architecture</a> and <a href="https://www.ecchr.eu/en/about-us/">ECCHR</a>, is supported by the <a href="https://www.glanlaw.org/">Global Legal Action Network</a>. We&rsquo;re speaking soon.</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>We aim to provide a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material, which demonstrates chain of custody and durable preservation.</dc:description><dc:date>2021-07-26T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence/</guid><description>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts</em></p>
<p>It would be difficult to explain our ambitions for the Digital Evidence Toolkit without first defining ‘digital evidence,’ a term used to describe any information stored in a digital format that is related to any future or ongoing litigation. This evidence may be stored on physical devices (such as smartphones, computers, or hard drives), or transmitted on the internet.</p>
<p>Advocacy groups have noted that the storage and preservation of digital evidence, whether it be online or on a device, both come with their own unique set of problems – see for example <a href="https://ibanet-org.zoom.us/rec/play/3xubOfazOciZXoUvGEtxNTOiwaQ1lO4wsGrObKjms0kJOL3DmbCR0JERAlHObEMaK6GH85F7cwJf8hcH.KFL67C_8WMqCUSGa?startTime=1605715248000&amp;&amp;_x_zm_rtaid=uRGfAxH-TOWn_Byx9AncRA.1606221810020.4054607a6db9ce7bad94be8bf9561faf&amp;&amp;_x_zm_rhtaid=792">this IBA panel moderated by EyeWitness director Wendy Betts</a>.</p>
<p>Physical devices on the one hand are subject to damage within areas of conflict or harsh environments, and even when properly cared for, devices may be seized by authorities at military checkpoints or border crossings; resulting in evidence lost.</p>
<p>Online, there are a multitude of challenges presented when trying to preserve digital evidence. Major ones are the automated flagging and deletions systems on platforms such as YouTube, Facebook, Twitter. Due to the often violent and graphic nature of pictures and videos uploaded from regions facing human-caused atrocities, original material containing potentially pertinent evidence may be automatically deleted, especially if the content is flagged.</p>
<p>Content distributed online is also victim of targeted censorship, and link rot – the phenomenon associated with how the web decays over time as hyperlinks fail to point to their intended target and as remote resources become unresponsive.</p>
<h2 id="admissibility-of-a-piece-of-evidence-is-not-always-a-given">Admissibility of a piece of evidence is not always a given</h2>
<p>Ultimately, what distinguishes &lsquo;digital&rsquo; evidence from any other form of evidence is that at its finest granularity it is composed of &lsquo;digits&rsquo; — arrangements of ones and zeros. Despite the seemingly unbiased method of recording digital information as either True or False (either “1” or “0”), when presented in legal settings digital information is not guaranteed to be admissible evidence.</p>
<p>With the large volume of disinformation present online and the inherent ‘plasticity’ of digital information — that is, its ability to be altered, rewritten, or deleted — it is unsurprising that digital evidence is subject to great scrutiny during juridical processes. Needless to say, just because a picture or video depicts something does not guarantee it is authentic and any alternative to this thinking could give weight to potentially falsified evidence.</p>
<p>The key to establishing the evidentiary value of a piece of evidence is respecting its ‘chain of custody’. In a <a href="https://blog.witness.org/2020/04/making-your-metadata-matter-part-2/">two-part blog post</a> by Wendy Betts and Raquel Vazquez Llorente (the Director and Senior Legal Advisor of eyeWitness to Atrocities, respectively) elaborate on the importance of the chain of custody in legal proceedings, stating “the key to chain of custody is proving that the footage remains unchanged from the time it was captured. While this might not be always possible for human rights defenders, the metadata collected by a documentation app can help demonstrate chain of custody, but it needs to meet some conditions. The key concepts here are when was the metadata captured, and who potentially had the ability to alter it.”</p>
<p>In Betts and Vazquez Llorente’s post, they touch on two critical points related to digital evidence preservation. The first is that establishing chain of custody serves to authenticate evidence by establishing its original source, digital-pathway of movement and the absence of opportunities for this information to be altered — effectively, acting similarly to an ‘alibi’. The second is the importance of preserving the necessary metadata, which ties the now authenticated evidence to a time and place, thus giving the material its necessary contextual and legal relevance as evidence.</p>
<p>(For context, EyeWitness&rsquo; lead product, a documentation app handles this problem at the source by offering a camera mode, thus starting the chain of custody claim from the moment of capture – whereas the Digital Evidence Toolkit deals with research material collected after-the-fact)</p>
<p>An early example of digital evidence preservation which is helpful in conceptualising digital ‘chain of custody’ was the process of procuring evidence during the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia (ICTY), where digital information whether it be data from a computer hard drive or digital photography was treated as if it were analog to ensure the proper handling of evidence. In Susan Schuppli’s <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/material-witness">‘Material Witness’</a>, she writes “a series of images taken or produced with a digital camera by an OTP (Office of the Prosecutor) investigator in the aftermath of a war crime would be burned to disk, the CD carrying these images photographed and labeled, the image of this CD carrying the images taken at the crime scene filed with the Tribunals’ Registry and given a unique number.” While this method of evidence procurement was more suited to the period, in principle the same process can be applied to digital evidence today where a unique number is assigned to the evidence once its chain of custody is established and the evidence is in an immutable state.</p>
<p>Where in the past a burned-CD labelled with a unique number would suffice, nowadays the sheer volume of data coming out of mass atrocity crimes in some places makes this particular solution, er, unpractical. To say the least.</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts</dc:description><dc:date>2021-07-18T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item><item><title>Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Basile Simon</author><dc:creator>Basile Simon</dc:creator><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved/</guid><description>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&amp;#39;d love your help</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&rsquo;d love your help</em></p>
<p>What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn&rsquo;t admissible within court because it was improperly&rsquo; handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the complete absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived - future prosecution efforts continue to remain in jeopardy.</p>
<p>Whether you practice journalism, law, or advocate within civil society, the entanglement of digital technology and our physical environment has become commonplace. While more accessible forms of technology have given civilians the tools to readily record media and data — that has the &lsquo;potential&rsquo; to be admissible evidence in court — the absence of any standardised legal frameworks regarding how data should be collected and stored presents a very important and contemporary problem: <em><strong>How do we forensically handle digital evidence?</strong></em></p>
<p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) is a project bringing together expert voices from the field to talk about the complexities of handling digital evidence. It aims to create a robust, immutable archiving software. Designed to preserve the digital chain of custody to a high enough standard to sustain the intense juridical pressure and scrutiny presented by state-actors or multi-national corporations. Raising the bar of what a group of dedicated individuals can do to protect the material they collect.</p>
<p>The project is currently in development and frankly there is so much to read and know that we&rsquo;d love to hear from you. Please reach out to <a href="mailto:basile@digitalevidencetoolkit.org">basile@digitalevidencetoolkit.org</a> 👋</p>
<p>(or join this newsletter for more)</p>
]]></content:encoded><dc:description>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&amp;#39;d love your help</dc:description><dc:date>2021-07-10T00:00:00Z</dc:date><dc:rights>CC BY 4.0</dc:rights><dc:license>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:license></item></channel></rss>