<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>News on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/</link><description>Recent content in News on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Copyright © 2021-25, Basile Simon</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Support for S3-class cloud storage</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/support-for-s3-class-cloud-storage/</guid><description>For relatively obvious reasons, we are working towards supporting teams and groups who wish to contribute to a single, collective repository of archived material.
The first step in this direction is to open up the data storage options, so archived records can be browsed by several people.
We’ve just released the Toolkit v.0.11.0 which now supports S3-class cloud storage as both a destination and a source – in plain English, the Toolkit can now replicate its archives to the cloud and serve data from it.</description></item><item><title>Getting Started</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/getting-started/</guid><description>“It&amp;rsquo;s not you – it&amp;rsquo;s me” If the instructions in this guide feel a bit much, it&amp;rsquo;s likely because the Toolkit is still an alpha-version software which assumes a certain technical knowledge. There are technical solutions to simplifying this setup, but these were not prioritised.
🙏 If this is something you have expertise with and are happy to help, do reach out at **basile@digitalevidencetoolkit.org** Setting up the ledger The Toolkit requires a working connection with Amazon Web Services, and thus that you have some kind of well-permissioned account or IAM role.</description></item><item><title>End of grant announcement: the Toolkit is now MVP!</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/end-of-grant-announcement-the-toolkit-is-now-mvp/</guid><description>The DEPToolkit is a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material.
With only one click of the mouse, the material will be archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody and stored durably. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to go back to search through and annotate the material, and to export working copies of said material for publication and dissemination.
A database built thusly can be handed to a prosecutor ten years down the line, and they will be able to say with mathematical certainty: “the material in this archive is identical and contemporary to the one saved at the time, ten years ago.</description></item><item><title>Addressing the Berkeley protocol</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/addressing-the-berkeley-protocol/</guid><description>The leading light in terms of what we&amp;rsquo;re shooting for is the Berkeley Protocol on Digital Open Source Investigations. The Protocol defines an adequate preservation as respecting certain criteria.
Here&amp;rsquo;s how the Digital Evidence Toolkit follows these guidelines:
Authenticity &amp;ldquo;A digital item remains unchanged from when it was collected&amp;rdquo;
The Toolkit preserves content and authenticity proofs (SHA256 hashes of all files and bundles, a U.S. federal standard) separately and implements both the verification of an item and the lookup of a collection of items in the archive.</description></item><item><title>Newsletter #4: Time(stamped), Time(lapsed)</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%234-timestamped-timelapsed/</guid><description>Time. Dates. Data points in the legal battle over the value of pieces of evidence. But are they really this hard, indisputable and demonstrable?
Metadata is supposed to describe a digital medium – the word comes from meta: “referring to itself, or to something of its own type,” reads the Cambridge Dictionary. Think of the date at which a picture was taken, the model of scanner used to digitise a piece of paper, a location somewhere on the planet added by the uploader of a video, as well as its description&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%233-our-idea-to-preserve-digital-evidence/</guid><description>_(In case you missed it last week, the previous issue of this newsletter, “Wait, digital evidence?” in which we touch on chain of custody and admissibility, can be found here)__
It&amp;rsquo;s maybe time to clarify a few things about what the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit is and does*, from the two original thoughts:
Content living online is at risk. Deletion, link rot, censorship, accidental destruction – you name it. The social internet may be great at surfacing and disseminating information but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty terrible at preserving it.</description></item><item><title>Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%232-wait-digital-evidence/</guid><description>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts
It would be difficult to explain our ambitions for the Digital Evidence Toolkit without first defining ‘digital evidence,’ a term used to describe any information stored in a digital format that is related to any future or ongoing litigation. This evidence may be stored on physical devices (such as smartphones, computers, or hard drives), or transmitted on the internet.</description></item><item><title>Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/news/newsletter-%231-what-is-the-digital-evidence-toolkit-and-how-can-you-become-involved/</guid><description>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&amp;rsquo;d love your help
What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn&amp;rsquo;t admissible within court because it was improperly&amp;rsquo; handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the complete absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived - future prosecution efforts continue to remain in jeopardy.</description></item></channel></rss>