<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title>
    <link>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Newsletter #4: Time(stamped), Time(lapsed)</title>
      <link>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-4/</guid>
      <description>Time. Dates. Data points in the legal battle over the value of pieces of evidence. But are they really this hard, indisputable and demonstrable?
Metadata is supposed to describe a digital medium – the word comes from meta: “referring to itself, or to something of its own type,” reads the Cambridge Dictionary. Think of the date at which a picture was taken, the model of scanner used to digitise a piece of paper, a location somewhere on the planet added by the uploader of a video, as well as its description&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newsletter #3: Our idea to preserve digital evidence</title>
      <link>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-3/</guid>
      <description>_(In case you missed it last week, the previous issue of this newsletter, “Wait, digital evidence?” in which we touch on chain of custody and admissibility, can be found here)__
It&amp;rsquo;s maybe time to clarify a few things about what the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit is and does*, from the two original thoughts:
 Content living online is at risk. Deletion, link rot, censorship, accidental destruction – you name it. The social internet may be great at surfacing and disseminating information but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty terrible at preserving it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newsletter #2: Wait, digital evidence?</title>
      <link>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-2/</guid>
      <description>A brief intro to its unclear evidentiary value and admissibility before the courts
It would be difficult to explain our ambitions for the Digital Evidence Toolkit without first defining ‘digital evidence,’ a term used to describe any information stored in a digital format that is related to any future or ongoing litigation. This evidence may be stored on physical devices (such as smartphones, computers, or hard drives), or transmitted on the internet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newsletter #1: What is the “Digital Evidence Toolkit” and how can you become involved?</title>
      <link>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://basilesimon.fr/test-proto/public/newsletter-1/</guid>
      <description>A new threat looms over international prosecutions – I&amp;rsquo;d love your help
What if digital evidence collected over a period of years, or even decades, wasn&amp;rsquo;t admissible within court because it was improperly&#39; handled by individuals with nothing but the best intentions? In the complete absence of internationally recognised legal standards regarding how digital forms of evidence should be recorded, handled, and archived - future prosecution efforts continue to remain in jeopardy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
