<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Tools on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/</link><description>Recent content in Tools on The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>Copyright © 2021-25, Basile Simon</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Coming Soon: Digital Evidence Toolkit x Microsoft Relativity</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/microsoft-relativity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/microsoft-relativity/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seamlessly integrate Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) into Microsoft Relativity, bringing powerful evidence validation, metadata analysis, secure archiving, and chain-of-custody tracking directly into your legal workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This integration enhances eDiscovery, compliance, and digital forensics, allowing law firms, investigators, and litigation teams to verify, preserve, and present digital evidence with unmatched security and integrity.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="what-to-expect">What to Expect&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Automated Metadata Validation&lt;/strong> – Detect inconsistencies and verify authenticity within Relativity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Chain of Custody Tracking&lt;/strong> – Ensure tamper-proof documentation from collection to courtroom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Secure Archiving –&lt;/strong> Store digital evidence with cryptographic verification for long-term integrity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Court-Ready Exports&lt;/strong> – Generate legally admissible reports within Relativity’s case management system.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Of High Interest? Be in Touch&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Turn WordPress into a Powerful Evidence Management Platform</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/wordpress-plugin/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/wordpress-plugin/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) WordPress Plugin transforms WordPress into a secure, verifiable evidence management system, allowing teams to capture, authenticate, and manage digital content with built-in chain-of-custody tracking and court-ready exports. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re an investigative journalist, a legal professional, or a compliance officer, our plugin ensures that every piece of digital evidence is verifiable and tamper-proof.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="key-features">Key Features:&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Metadata Analysis&lt;/strong> – Automatically extract, verify, and log key metadata for every uploaded file.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Content Credentials Integration&lt;/strong> – Display cryptographic proof of authenticity and authorship using Content Credentials technology.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Chain of Custody Tracking&lt;/strong> – Ensure secure, tamper-proof documentation of every change, action, and transfer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Court-Ready Exports&lt;/strong> – Generate reports in legally admissible formats with a verifiable audit trail.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>✅ Seamless WordPress Integration&lt;/strong> – Works with existing media libraries, post types, and workflows.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="how-it-works">How It Works&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Built with PHP and JavaScript, the DEPT WordPress Plugin seamlessly integrates with your WordPress media library and enables automatic metadata analysis upon file upload. Using SHA-256 hashing and a tamper-proof ledger database (QLDB or alternative immutable storage), each file’s authenticity is recorded and tracked.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Archive Webpages with Proof of Integrity</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/webpage-archiving/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/webpage-archiving/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit (DEPT) offers a seamless way to capture and authenticate web content while ensuring a verifiable chain of custody. Our one-click browser extension allows you to archive webpages with cryptographic proof, making them admissible in legal, journalistic, and research contexts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Every saved webpage is stored alongside metadata, DNS records, and a tamper-proof ledger entry, ensuring long-term integrity. Whether you’re investigating misinformation, documenting critical online evidence, or preserving web pages for compliance, our solution guarantees authenticity you can trust.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Original DEPToolkit prototype</title><link>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/original-dept-prototype/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://digitalevidencetoolkit.org/tools/original-dept-prototype/</guid><description>&lt;p>Welcome to the documentation of the Digital Evidence Preservation Toolkit, a one-click tool to archive and annotate webpages while demonstrating chain of custody throughout. The Toolkit is a proof-of-concept software for researchers and small teams sifting through online material.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With only one click of the mouse, the material will be &lt;strong>archived in a framework demonstrating chain of custody&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>stored durably&lt;/strong>. Once included in the growing database, users will be able to &lt;strong>go back to search through&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>annotate the material&lt;/strong>, and to &lt;strong>export working copies&lt;/strong> of said material for publication and dissemination.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>